This may sound strange,
قد يبدو هذا غريبا،
but I'm a big fan of the concrete block.
لكنني معجبة جدا بوحدات الخرسانة.
The first concrete blocks were manufactured in 1868
أولى وحدات الخرسانة تم تصنيعها سنة 1868
with a very simple idea:
بفكرة بسيطة جدا:
modules made of cement of a fixed measurement
وحدات مصنوعة من الاسمنت بقياسات ثابتة
that fit together.
متوافقة مع بعضها البعض.
Very quickly concrete blocks became
أصبحت وحدات الخرسانة بسرعة
the most-used construction unit in the world.
أكثر وحدات البناء استخداما في العالم.
They enabled us to to build things that were larger than us,
أتاحت لنا بناء أشياء أكبر منا،
buildings, bridges,
بنايات، أبراج،
one brick at a time.
آجرة واحدة كل مرة.
Essentially concrete blocks had become
وقد صارت وحدات الخرسانة في الأساس
the building block of our time.
وحدات بناء زمننا.
Almost a hundred years later in 1947,
لاحقا وبعد حوالي مئة عام، سنة 1947،
LEGO came up with this.
جاءت ليغو بهذه.
It was called the Automatic Binding Brick.
كانت تدعى الربط التلقائي للآجر.
And in a few short years,
وبعد سنوات قصيرة،
LEGO bricks took place in every household.
تواجد طوب ليغو في كل منزل.
It's estimated that over 400 billion bricks have been produced --
ويقدر أنه تم إنتاج 400 مليار طوب --
or 75 bricks for every person on the planet.
أو 75 طوبا لكل شخص على الكوكب.
You don't have to be an engineer
ليس عليك أن تكون مهندسا
to make beautiful houses, beautiful bridges, beautiful buildings.
لبناء بيوت جميلة وجسور جميلة وبنايات جميلة.
LEGO made it accessible.
جعلتها ليغو في المتناول.
LEGO has essentially taken the concrete block, the building block of the world,
أساسا قد أخذت ليغو وحدات الخرسانة، ووحدات بناء العالم،
and made it into the building block
وحولتها إلى وحدات بناء
of our imagination.
مخيلاتنا.
Meanwhile the exact same year,
وفي هذا الأثناء من نفس السنة بالضبط،
at Bell Labs the next revolution was about to be announced,
في مختبرات بيل كانت الثورة الموالية على وشك أن يعلن عنها،
the next building block.
وحدات البناء التالية.
The transistor was a small plastic unit
كان الترانزستور وحدة بلاستيكية صغيرة
that would take us from a world
ستأخذنا من عالم
of static bricks piled on top of each other
الوحدات الثابتة مكومة فوق بعضها البعض
to a world where everything was interactive.
إلى عالم حيث كل شيء تفاعلي.
Like the concrete block,
مثل وحدات البناء،
the transistor allows you to build
يسمح لنا الترانزستور ببناء
much larger, more complex circuits, one brick at a time.
دوائر أكبر بكثير وأكثر تعقيدا، وحدة كل مرة.
But there's a main difference:
لكن هناك اختلافا رئيسيا:
The transistor was only for experts.
الترانزستور كان للخبراء فقط.
I personally don't accept this,
شخصيا لا أقبل هذا،
that the building block of our time
أن وحدات البناء في زمننا
is reserved for experts,
مخصصة للخبراء،
so I decided to change that.
لذا قررت تغيير ذلك.
Eight years ago when I was at the Media Lab,
قبل ثمانية سنوات حين كنت في مختبر ميديا،
I started exploring this idea
بدأت في استكشاف هذه الفكرة
of how to put the power of engineers
في كيفية وضع قدرات المهندسين
in the hands of artists and designers.
في أيدي الفنانين والمصممين.
A few years ago I started developing littleBits.
قبل بضع سنوات بدأت بتطوير ليتل-بيتس.
Let me show you how they work.
دعوني أريكم كيف تشتغل.
LittleBits are electronic modules
ليتل-بيتس هي وحدات إلكترونية
with each one specific function.
لكل واحدة وظيفة محددة.
They're pre-engineered
إنها مهندسة مسبقا
to be light, sound,
لتكون ضوء وصوتا
motors and sensors.
ومحركات ومستشعرات.
And the best part about it
وأفضل جزء بخصوصها
is they snap together with magnets.
هو أنها تلتصق ببعضها بمغانط.
So you can't put them the wrong way.
لذا فإننا لا نستطيع وضعها معا بطريقة خاطئة.
The bricks are color-coded.
هذه اللبنات مرمزة لونيا.
Green is output, blue is power,
الأخضر هو المخرج والأزرق هو الطاقة
pink is input and orange is wire.
والوردي هو المدخل والبرتقالي هو السلك.
So all you need to do is snap a blue to a green
وبالتالي كل ما تحتاجه هو ربط الأزرق بالأخضر
and very quickly you can start making larger circuits.
وبسرعة كبيرة يمكن أن تبدأ في بناء دوائر أكبر.
You put a blue to a green,
تضع الأزرق على الأخضر،
you can make light.
يمكن أن تبني ضوء.
You can put a knob in between
يمكنك أن تضع مقبضا بينهما
and now you've made a little dimmer.
والآن قد صنعتم ضوء خافتا.
Switch out the knob
حولوا المقبض
for a pulse module,
من أجل وحدة نبض،
which is here,
والتي هي هنا،
and now you've made a little blinker.
وتكونون قد صنعتم وامضا صغيرا.
Add this buzzer
وهذه الصافرة
for some extra punch
من أجل أمر إضافي
and you've created a noise machine.
وتكونون قد أنشأتم آلة ضجيج.
I'm going to stop that.
سأقوم بإيقاف ذلك.
So beyond simple play,
لذا فوراء اللعب البسيط،
littleBits are actually pretty powerful.
ليتل-بيتس هي في الواقع قوية جدا.
Instead of having to program, to wire, to solder,
بدل الحاجة إلى البرمجة والربط واللحام
littleBits allow you to program
تتيح ليتل-بيتس لنا البرمجة
using very simple intuitive gestures.
باستخدام إشارات بديهية بسيطة.
So to make this blink faster or slower,
لجعل هذا يومض بشكل أسرع وأبطأ،
you would just turn this knob
ستقومون فقط بإدارة هذا المقبض
and basically make it pulse faster or slower.
وجعله أساسا يومض بشكل أسرع أو أبطأ.
The idea behind littleBits
الفكرة خلف ليتل-بيتس
is that it's a growing library.
هو أنها مكتبة متنامية.
We want to make every single interaction in the world
نريد أن نجعل كل تفاعل في العالم
into a ready-to-use brick.
طوبا جاهزا للاستخدام.
Lights, sounds, solar panels, motors --
الضوء والصوت والألواح الشمسية والمحركات --
everything should be accessible.
كل شيء يجب أن يكون متاحا.
We've been giving littleBits to kids and seeing them play with them.
أعطينا ليتل-بيتس لأطفال وراقبناهم يلعبون بها.
And it's been an incredible experience.
وكانت تجربة مذهلة.
The nicest thing is how they start to understand
أجمل شيء هو كيف بدؤوا في فهم
the electronics around them from everyday
الإلكترونيات حولهم كل يوم
that they don't learn at schools.
والذي لا يتعلمونه في المدارس.
For example, how a nightlight works,
على سبيل المثال، كيف تشتغل الأضواء الليلية،
or why an elevator door stays open,
أو كيف يبقى باب المصعد مفتوحا،
or how an iPod responds to touch.
أو كيف يتجاوب الآيبود مع اللمس.
We've also been taking littleBits to design schools.
قمنا كذلك بأخذ ليتل-بيتس إلى مدارس التصميم.
So for example, we've had designers
لذا على سبيل المثال، كان لدينا مصممون
with no experience with electronics whatsoever
بدون أي خبرة أيا كانت في الإلكترونيات
start to play with littleBits as a material.
بدؤوا في اللعب بـ: ليتل-بيتسر كمادة.
Here you see, with felt and paper water bottles,
هنا ترون، مع اللباد وقنينات الماء الورقية،
we have Geordie making ...
لدينا جيوردي يصنع ...
(Clanging)
(رنين)
(Buzzing)
(طنين)
A few weeks ago we took littleBits to RISD
قبل بضعة أسابيع أخذنا ليتل-بيتس إلى كلية ريزدي
and gave them to some designers
وأعطيناها لبعض المصممين
with no experience in engineering whatsoever --
بدون خبرة أيا كانت في الهندسة --
just cardboard, wood and paper -- and told them "Make something."
فقط ورق مقوى وخشب وورق -- وقلنا لهم "اصنعوا شيئا."
Here's an example of a project they made,
هذا مثال على مشروع صنعوه،
a motion-activated confetti canon ball.
مدفع ورق ملون يتم تفعيله بالحركة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But wait, this is actually my favorite project.
لكن انتظروا، هذا في الواقع مشروعي المفضل.
It's a lobster made of playdough
إنه سرطان البحر مصنوع من بلايدووغ
that's afraid of the dark.
يخاف من الظلام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
To these non-engineers, littleBits became another material,
بالنسبة لغير المهندسين هؤلاء، ليتل-بيتس صار مادة أخرى،
electronics became just another material.
الإلكترونيات صارت مجرد مادة أخرى.
And we want to make this material accessible to everyone.
ونريد أن نجعل هذه المادة متاحة للجميع.
So littleBits is open-source.
لذا فليتل-بيتس هي مفتوحة المصدر.
You can go on the website, download all the design files, make them yourself.
يمكنكم الذهاب إلى الموقع الإلكتروني وتحميل كل ملفات التصميم وبناءها بأنفسكم.
We want to encourage a world
نريد أن نشجع عالما
of creators, of inventors, of contributors,
من المبدعين والمخترعين والمساهمين،
because this world that we live in,
لأن العالم الذي نعيش فيه،
this interactive world, is ours.
هذا العالم التفاعلي، هو ملكنا.
So go ahead and start inventing.
إذن فلتمضوا قدما ولتبدؤوا في الاختراع.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)